<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../../xsl/thesis.xsl" ?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/5.0b5/rng/docbookxi.rng" type="xml"?>
<article xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
    <info>
        <title>R1.D0-2008 [DRAFT] Box Social Rules of Incorporation</title>
        <author>
            <personname>
                <firstname>David</firstname>
                <othername>Lachlan</othername>
                <surname>Smith</surname>
            </personname>
        </author>
        <legalnotice>
            <para>Permission is granted to copy, distribute and/or modify this document under the
                terms of the GNU Free Documentation License, Version 1.2 as published by the Free
                Software Foundation; with no Invariant Sections, no Front-Cover Texts, and no
                Back-Cover Texts. A copy of the license is included in the section entitled "GNU
                Free Documentation License".</para>
        </legalnotice>
        <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="standard_includes\logo.png" width="6.0cm"> </imagedata>
            </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
    </info>
    <section>
        <title>Interpretation</title>
        <para>In these rules-</para>
        <para><emphasis>Act</emphasis> means the Associations Incorporation Act 1981.</para>
        <para>
            <emphasis>present-</emphasis>
        </para>
        <orderedlist numeration="loweralpha">
            <listitem>
                <para>at a management committee meeting; or</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>at a general meeting,</para>
            </listitem>
        </orderedlist>
        <para>A word or expression that is not defined in these model rules, but is defined in the
            Act has, if the context permits, the meaning given in the Act.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Name</title>
        <para>The name of the incorporated association is Box Social Incorporated (<emphasis>the
                association</emphasis>).</para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Objects</title>
        <para>The object of the association are-</para>
        <orderedlist numeration="loweralpha">
            <listitem>
                <para>to promote the global community; and</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>to promote community development of the Box Social software; and</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>to maintain an active installation of the Box Social software on the internet;
                    and</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>to do so in the spirit of the Free Software Foundation.</para>
            </listitem>
        </orderedlist>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Powers</title>
        <para>The association has the powers of an individual.</para>
        <para>The association may, for example-</para>
        <orderedlist numeration="loweralpha">
            <listitem>
                <para>enter into contracts; and</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>acquire, hold, deal with, and dispose of property; and</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>make charges for services and facilities it supplies; and</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>do other things necessary of convenient to be done in carrying out its
                    affairs.</para>
            </listitem>
        </orderedlist>
        <para>The association make take over the funds and other assets and liabilities of the
            present unincorporated association known as Box Social (the <emphasis>unincorporated
                association</emphasis>).</para>
        <para>The association may also issue secured and unsecured notes, debentures and debenture
            stock for the association.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Classes of members</title>
        <para>The membership of the association consists of ordinary members, and any of the
            following classes of members-</para>
        <orderedlist numeration="loweralpha">
            <listitem>
                <para>Community member</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Developer</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Translator</para>
            </listitem>
        </orderedlist>

        <para>The number of ordinary members is unlimited. Acceptance as an ordinary member requires
            payment of the membership fee.</para>
        <para>The number of community members is unlimited. A community member is one who has joined
            http://boxsocial.net and has not paid a membership fee, and does not belong to another
            class of members.</para>
        <para>Membership level of developer is open to those who have source control commit access
            to Box Social internals, or any application whose Intellectual Property belongs to the
            association, and does not solely make language contributions.</para>
        <para>Acceptance to this level of membership is by application to the Lead Developer.
            Approval shall be granted or denied by the Lead Developer.</para>
        <para>Membership level of translator is open to those who make language
        contributions.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Automatic membership</title>
        <para>A person who, on the day the association is incorporated, was a member of the
            unincorporated association and who, on or before a day fixed by the management
            committee, agrees in writing to become a member of the incorporated association, must be
            admitted by the management committee-</para>
        <orderedlist numeration="loweralpha">
            <listitem>
                <para>to the equivalent class of membership of the association as the member held in
                    the unincorporated association; or</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>if there is no equivalent class of membership-as an ordinary member.</para>
            </listitem>
        </orderedlist>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>New membership</title>
        <para>An applicant for ordinary membership of the association must be proposed by 1 member
            of the association (the proposer) and seconded by another member (the seconder).</para>
        <para>An application for membership must be-</para>
        <orderedlist numeration="loweralpha">
            <listitem>
                <para>in writing; and</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>signed by the applicant and the applicant's proposer and seconder; and</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>in the form decided by the management committee.</para>
            </listitem>
        </orderedlist>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Membership fees</title>
        <para>The membership fee for each ordinary membership and for each other class of membership
            (if any)-</para>
        <orderedlist numeration="loweralpha">
            <listitem>
                <para>is the amount decided by the members from time to time at a general meeting;
                    and</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>is payable when, and in the way, the management committee decides.</para>
            </listitem>
        </orderedlist>
        <para>A member of the incorporated association who, before becoming a member, has paid the
            member’s annual subscription for membership of the unincorporated association on or
            before a day fixed by the management committee, is not liable to pay a further amount of
            annual subscription for the period before the day fixed by the management committee as
            the day on which the next annual subscription is payable.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Admission and rejection of new members</title>
        <para>The management committee must consider an application for membership at the next
            committee meeting held after it receives-</para>
        <orderedlist numeration="loweralpha">
            <listitem>
                <para>the application for membership; and</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>the appropriate membership fee for the application.</para>
            </listitem>
        </orderedlist>
        <para>The management committee must ensure that, as soon as possible after the person
            applies to become a member of the association, and before the management committee
            considers the person's application, the person is advised-</para>
        <orderedlist numeration="loweralpha">
            <listitem>
                <para>whether or not the association has public liability insurance; and</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>if the association has public liability insurance-the amount of the
                insurance.</para>
            </listitem>
        </orderedlist>
        <para>The management committee must decide at the meeting whether to accept or reject the
            application.</para>
        <para>If a majority of the members of the management committee present at the meeting vote
            to accept the applicant as a member, the application must be accepted as a member for
            the class of membership applied for.</para>
        <para>The secretary of the association must, as soon as practicable after the management
            committee decides to accept or reject an application, give the application a written
            notice of the decision.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>When membership ends</title>
        <para>A member may resign from the association by giving a written notice of resignation to
            the secretary.</para>
        <para>The resignation takes effect at-</para>
        <orderedlist numeration="loweralpha">
            <listitem>
                <para>the time the notice is received by the secretary; or</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>if a later time is stated in the notice-the later time.</para>
            </listitem>
        </orderedlist>
        <para>The management committee may terminate a member's membership if the member-</para>
        <orderedlist numeration="loweralpha">
            <listitem>
                <para>is convicted of an indictable office; or</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>does not comply with any of the provisions of these rules; or</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>has membership fees in arrears for at least 2 months; or</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>conducts himself or herself in a way considered to be injurious or prejudicial
                    to the character or interests of the association.</para>
            </listitem>
        </orderedlist>
        <para>Before the management committee terminates a member's membership, the committee must
            give the member a full and fair opportunity to show why the membership should not be
            terminated.</para>
        <para>If, after considering all representations made by the member, the management committee
            decides to terminate the membership, the secretary of the committee must give the member
            a written notice of the decision.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Appeal against rejection or termination of membership</title>
        <para>A person whose application for membership has been rejected, or whose membership has
            been terminated, may give the secretary written notice of the person's intention to
            appeal against the decision.</para>
        <para>A notice of intention to appeal must be given to the secretary within 1 month after
            the person receives written notice of the decision.</para>
        <para>If the secretary receives a notice of intention to appeal, the secretary must, within
            1 month after receiving the notice, call a general meeting to decide the appeal.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>General meeting to decide appeal</title>
        <para>The general meeting to decide an appeal must be held within 3 months after the
            secretary receives the notice of intention to appeal.</para>
        <para>At the meeting, the applicant must be given a full and fair opportunity to show why
            the application should not be rejected or the membership should not be terminated.</para>
        <para>Also, the management committee and the members of the committee who rejected the
            application or terminated the membership must be given a full and fair opportunity to
            show why the application should be rejected or the membership should be terminated.</para>
        <para>An appeal must be decided by a majority vote of the members present and eligible to
            vote at the meeting.</para>
        <para>If a person whose application for membership has been rejected does not appeal against
            the decision within 1 month after receiving written notice of the decision, or the
            person appeals but the appeal is unsuccessful, the secretary must, as soon as
            practicable, refund the membership fee paid by the person.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Register of members</title>
        <para>The management committee must keep a register of members of the association.</para>
        <para>THe register must include the following particulars for each member-</para>
        <orderedlist numeration="loweralpha">
            <listitem>
                <para>the full name of the member;</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>the postal or residential address of the member;</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>the date of admission as a member;</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>the date of death or time of resignation of the member;</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>details about the termination or reinstatement of membership;</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>any other particulars the management committee or the members at a general
                    meeting decide.</para>
            </listitem>
        </orderedlist>
        <para>The register must be open for inspection by members of the association at all
            reasonable times.</para>
        <para>A member must contact the secretary to arrange an inspection of the register.</para>
        <para>However, the management committee may, on the application of a member of the
            association withhold information about the member (other than the member's full name)
            from the register available for inspection if the management committee has reasonable
            grounds for believing the disclosure of the information would put the member at risk of
            harm.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Prohibition on use of information on register of members</title>
        <para>A member of the association must not-</para>
        <orderedlist numeration="loweralpha">
            <listitem>
                <para>use information obtained from the register of members of the association to
                    contact, or send material to, another member of the association for the purpose
                    of advertising for political, religions, charitable, or commercial purposes;
                or</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>disclose information obtained from the register to someone else, knowing that
                    the information is likely to be used to contact, or send material to, another
                    member of the association for the purpose of advertising for political,
                    religious, charitable or commercial purposes.</para>
            </listitem>
        </orderedlist>
        <para>Subrule (1) does not apply if the use of disclosure of the information is approved by
            the association.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Appointment or election of secretary</title>
        <para>The secretary must be an individual residing in Queensland, or in another State but
            not more than 65 km from the Queensland border, who is-</para>
        <orderedlist numeration="loweralpha">
            <listitem>
                <para>a member of the association elected by the association as secretary; or</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>any of the following persons appointed by the management committee as
                    secretary-</para>
                <orderedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>a member of the association's management committee;</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>another member of the association;</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>another person.</para>
                    </listitem>
                </orderedlist>
            </listitem>
        </orderedlist>
        <para>If the association has not elected an interim officer as secretary for the association
            before its incorporation, the members of the management committee must ensure a
            secretary is appointed or elected for the association within 1 month after
            incorporation.</para>
        <para>If a vacancy happens in the office of secretary, the members of the management
            committee must ensure a secretary is appointed or elected for the association within 1
            month after the vacancy happens.</para>
        <para>If the management committee appoints a person mentioned in subrule (1)(b)(ii) as
            secretary, other than to fill a casual vacancy on the management committee, the person
            does not become a member of the management committee.</para>
        <para>However, if the management committee appoints person mentioned in subrule (1)(b)(ii)
            as secretary to fill a casual vacancy on the management committee, the person becomes a
            member of the management committee.</para>
        <para>If the management committee appoints a person mentioned in subrule (1)(b)(iii) as
            secretary, the person does not become a member of the management committee.</para>
        <para>In this rule-</para>
        <para>casual vacancy, on a management committee, means a vacancy that happens when an
            elected member of the management committee resigns, dies, or otherwise stops holding
            office.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Removal of secretary</title>
        <para>The management committee of the association may at any time remove a person appointed
            by the committee as the secretary.</para>
        <para>If the management committee removes a secretary who is a person mentioned in rule
            15(1)(b)(i), the person remains a member of the management committee.</para>
        <para>If the management committee removes a secretary who is a person mentioned in rule
            15(1)(b)(ii) and who has been appointed to a casual vacancy on the management committee
            under rule 15(5), the person remains a member of the management committee.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Functions of secretary</title>
        <para>The secretary's functions include, but are not limited to-</para>
        <para>calling meetings of the association, including preparing notices of a meeting and of
            the business to be conducted at a meeting in consultation with the president of the
            association; and</para>
        <para>keeping minutes of each meeting; and</para>
        <para>keeping copies of all correspondence and other documents relation to the association;
            and</para>
        <para>maintaining the register of members of the association.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Membership of management committee</title>
        <para>The management committee of the association consists of a president, treasurer, and
            any other members the association members elect at a general meeting.</para>
        <para>A member of the management committee, other than a secretary appointed by the
            management committee under rule 15(1)(b)(iii), must be a member of the association.</para>
        <para>At each annual general meeting of the association, the members of the management
            committee must retire from office, but are eligible on nomination, for re-election.</para>
        <para>A member of the association may be appointed to a casual vacancy on the management
            committee under rule 21.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Electing the management committee</title>
        <para>A member of the management committee may only be elected as follows-</para>
        <orderedlist numeration="loweralpha">
            <listitem>
                <para>any 2 members of the association may nominate another member (the candidate)
                    to serve as a member of the management committee;</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>the nomination must be-</para>
                <orderedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>in writing; and</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>signed by the candidate and the members who nominated him or her;
                        and</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>given to the secretary at least 14 days before the annual general
                            meeting at which the election is to be held;</para>
                    </listitem>
                </orderedlist>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>each member of the association present and eligible to vote at the annual
                    general meeting may vote for 1 candidate for each vacant position on the
                    management committee;</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>if, at the start of the meeting, there are not enough candidates nominated,
                    nominations may be taken from the floor of the meeting.</para>
            </listitem>
        </orderedlist>
        <para>A person may be a candidate only if the person-</para>
        <orderedlist numeration="loweralpha">
            <listitem>
                <para>is an adult; and</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>is not ineligible to be elected as a member under section 61A of the
                Act.</para>
            </listitem>
        </orderedlist>
        <para>A list of the candidates' names in alphabetic order, with the name of the members who
            nominated each candidate, must be posted in a conspicuous place in the office or usual
            place of meeting os the association for at least 7 days immediately preceding the annual
            general meeting.</para>
        <para>If required by the management committee, balloting lists must be prepared containing
            the names of the candidates in alphabetical order.</para>
        <para>The management committee must ensure that, before a candidate is elected as a member
            of the management committee, the candidate is advised-</para>
        <orderedlist numeration="loweralpha">
            <listitem>
                <para>whether or not the association has public liability insurance; and</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>if the association has public liability insurance-the amount of the
                insurance.</para>
            </listitem>
        </orderedlist>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Resignation, removal, or vacation of office of management committee member</title>
        <para>A member of the management committee may resign from the committee by giving written
            notice of resignation to the secretary.</para>
        <para>The resignation takes effect at-</para>
        <orderedlist numeration="loweralpha">
            <listitem>
                <para>the time the notice is received by the secretary; or</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>if a later time is stated in the notice-the later time.</para>
            </listitem>
        </orderedlist>
        <para>A member may be removed from office at a general meeting of the association if a
            majority of the members present and eligible to vote at the meeting vote in favour of
            removing the member.</para>
        <para>Before a vote of members is taken about removing the member from office, the member
            must be given a full and fair opportunity to show cause why he or she should not be
            removed from office.</para>
        <para>A member has not right of appeal against the member's removal from office under this
            rule.</para>
        <para>A member immediately vacates the office of member in the circumstances mentioned in
            section 64(s) of the Act.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Vacancies on the management committee</title>
        <para>If a casual vacancy happens on the management committee, the continuing members of the
            committee may appoint another member of the association to fill the vacancy until the
            next annual general meeting.</para>
        <para>The continuing members of the management committee may act despite a casual vacancy on
            the management committee.</para>
        <para>However, if the number of committee members is less than the number fixed under rule
            24(1) as a quorum of the management committee, the continuing members may act only to-</para>
        <orderedlist numeration="loweralpha">
            <listitem>
                <para>increase the number of management committee members to the number required for
                    quorum; or</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>call a general meeting of the association.</para>
            </listitem>
        </orderedlist>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Functions of management committee</title>
        <para>Subject to these rules or a resolution of the members of the association carried at a
            general meeting, the management committee has the general control and management of the
            administration of the affairs, property and funds of the association.</para>
        <para>The management committee has authority to interpret the meaning of these rules and any
            matter relating to the association on which the rules are silent, but any interpretation
            must have regard to the Act, including any regulation made under the Act.</para>
        <note>
            <para>The Act prevails if the association's rules are inconsistent with the Act-see
                section 1B of the Act.</para>
        </note>
        <para>The management committee may exercise the powers of the association-</para>
        <orderedlist numeration="loweralpha">
            <listitem>
                <para>to borrow, raise or secure payment of amounts in a way members of the
                    association decide; and</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>to secure the amounts mentioned in paragraph (a) or the payment or performance
                    of any debt, liability, contract, guarantee or other engagement incurred or to
                    be entered into by the association in any way, including by the issue of
                    debentures (perpetual or otherwise) charged upon the whole or part of the
                    association's property, both present and future; and</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>to purchase, redeem or pay off any securities issued; and</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>to borrow amounts from members and pay interest on the amounts borrowed;
                and</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>to mortgage or charge the whole or part of its property; and</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>to issue debentures and other securities, whether outright or as security for
                    any debt, liability or obligation of the association; and</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>to provide and pay off any securities issued; and</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>to invest in a way the members of the association may from time to time
                    decide.</para>
            </listitem>
        </orderedlist>
        <para>For subrule (3)(d), the rate of interest must not be more than the current rate being
            charged for overdrawn accounts on money lent (regardless of the term of the load) by-</para>
        <orderedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para>the financial institution for the association; or</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>if there is more than 1 financial institution for the association-the
                    financial institution nominated by the management committee.</para>
            </listitem>
        </orderedlist>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Meetings of management committee</title>
        <para>Subject to this rule, the management committee may meet and conduct its proceedings as
            it considers appropriate.</para>
        <para>The management committee must meet at least once every 4 months to exercise its
            functions.</para>
        <para>The management committee must decide how a meeting is to be called.</para>
        <para>Notice of a meeting is to be given in the way decided by the management committee.</para>
        <para>The management committee may hold meetings, or permit a committee member to take part
            in its meetings, by using any technology that reasonably allows the member to hear and
            take part in discussions as they happen.</para>
        <para>A committee member who participates in the meeting as mentioned in subrule (5) is
            taken to be present at the meeting.</para>
        <para>A question arising at a committee meeting is to be decided by a majority vote of
            members of the committee present at the meeting and, if the votes are equal, the
            question is decided in the negative.</para>
        <para>A member of the management committee must not vote on a question about a contract or
            proposed contract with the association if the member has an interest in the contract or
            proposed contract and, if the member does vote, the member's vote must not be counted.</para>
        <para>The president is to preside as chairperson at a management committee meeting.</para>
        <para>If there is no president or if the president is not present within 10 minutes after
            the time fixed for a management committee meeting, the members may choose 1 of their
            number to preside as chairperson at the meeting.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Quorum for, and adjournment of, management committee meeting</title>
        <para>At a management committee meeting, more than 50% of the members elected to the
            committee as at the close of the last general meeting of the members form a quorum.</para>
        <para>If there is no quorum within 30 minutes after the time fixed for management committee
            meeting called on the request of members of the committee, the meeting lapses.</para>
        <para>If there is no quorum within 30 minutes after the time fixed for a management
            committee meeting called other than on the request of the members of the committee-</para>
        <orderedlist numeration="loweralpha">
            <listitem>
                <para>the meeting is to be adjourned for at least 1 day; and</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>the members of the management committee who are present are to decide the day,
                    time, and place of the adjourned meeting.</para>
            </listitem>
        </orderedlist>
        <para>If, at an adjourned meeting mentioned in subrule (3), there is no quorum within 30
            minutes after the time fixed for the meeting, the meeting lapses.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Special meeting of management committee</title>
        <para>If the secretary receives a written request signed by at least 33% of the members of
            the management committee, the secretary must call a special meeting of the committee by
            giving each member of the committee notice of the meeting within 14 days after the
            secretary receives the request.</para>
        <para>If the secretary is unable or unwilling to call the special meeting, the president
            must call the meeting.</para>
        <para>A request for a special meeting must state-</para>
        <orderedlist numeration="loweralpha">
            <listitem>
                <para>why the special meeting is called; and</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>the business to be conducted at the meeting.</para>
            </listitem>
        </orderedlist>
        <para>A notice of a special meeting must state-</para>
        <orderedlist numeration="loweralpha">
            <listitem>
                <para>the day, time, and place of the meeting; and</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>the business to be conducted at the meeting.</para>
            </listitem>
        </orderedlist>
        <para>A special meeting of the management committee must be held within 14 days after notice
            of the meeting is given to the members of the management committee.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Minutes of management committee meetings</title>
        <para>The secretary must ensure full accurate minutes of all questions, matters,
            resolutions, and other proceedings of each management committee meeting are entered in a
            minute book.</para>
        <para>To ensure the accuracy of the minutes, the minutes of each management committee
            meeting must be signed by the chairperson of the meeting, or the chairperson of the next
            management committee meeting, verifying their accuracy.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Appointment of subcommittees</title>
        <para>The management committee may appoint a subcommittee consisting of members of the
            association considered appropriate by the committee to help with the conduct of the
            association's operations.</para>
        <para>A member of the subcommittee who is not a member of the management committee is not
            entitled to vote at a management committee meeting.</para>
        <para>A subcommittee may elect a chairperson of its meetings.</para>
        <para>If a chairperson is not elected, or if the chairperson is not present within 10
            minutes after the time fixed for a meeting, the members present may choose 1 of their
            number to be chairperson of the meeting.</para>
        <para>A subcommittee may meet and adjourn as it considers appropriate.</para>
        <para>A question arising at a subcommittee meeting is to be decided by a majority vote of
            the members present at the meeting and, if the votes are equal, the question is decided
            in the negative.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Acts not affected by defects or disqualifications</title>
        <para>An act performed by the management committee, a subcommittee or a person acting as a
            member of the management committee is taken to have been validly performed.</para>
        <para>Subrule (1) applies even if the act was performed when-</para>
        <orderedlist numeration="loweralpha">
            <listitem>
                <para>there was a defect in the appointment of a member of the management committee,
                    subcommittee or person acting as a member of the management committee; or</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>a management committee member, subcommittee member or person acting as a
                    member of the management committee was disqualified from being a member.</para>
            </listitem>
        </orderedlist>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Resolutions of management committee without meeting</title>
        <para>A written resolution signed by each member of the management committee is as valid and
            effectual as if it had been passed at a committee meeting that was properly called and
            held.</para>
        <para>A resolution mentioned in subrule (1) may consist of several documents in like form,
            each signed by 1 or more members of the committee.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>First annual general meeting</title>
        <para>The first annual general meeting must be held within 6 months after the end date of
            the association's first reportable financial year.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Subsequent annual general meetings</title>
        <para>Each subsequent annual general meeting must be held-</para>
        <orderedlist numeration="loweralpha">
            <listitem>
                <para>at least once each year; and</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>within 6 months after the end date of the association's reportable financial
                    year.</para>
            </listitem>
        </orderedlist>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Business to be conducted at annual general meeting of level 1 incorporated
            associations and particular level 2 and level 3 incorporated associations</title>
        <para>This rule applies only if the association is-</para>
        <orderedlist numeration="loweralpha">
            <listitem>
                <para>a level 1 incorporated association; or</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>a level 2 incorporated association to which section 59 of the Act applies;
                or</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>a level 3 incorporated association to which section 59 of the Act
                applies.</para>
            </listitem>
        </orderedlist>
        <para>The following business must be conducted at each annual general meeting of the
            association-</para>
        <orderedlist numeration="loweralpha">
            <listitem>
                <para>receiving the association's financial statement, and audit report, for the
                    last reportable financial year;</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>presenting the financial statement and audit report to the meeting for
                    adoption;</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>electing members of the management committee;</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>for a level 1 incorporated association-appointing an auditor or an accountant
                    for the present financial year;</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>for a level 2 incorporated association, or a level 3 incorporated association,
                    to which section 59 of the Act applies-appointing an auditor, an accountant or
                    an approved person for the present financial year.</para>
            </listitem>
        </orderedlist>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Business to be conducted at annual general meeting of other level 2 incorporated
            associations</title>
        <para>This rule applies only if the association is a level 2 incorporated association to
            which section 59A of the Act applies.</para>
        <para>The following business must be conducted at each annual general meeting of the
            association-</para>
        <orderedlist numeration="loweralpha">
            <listitem>
                <para>receiving the association's financial statement, and signed statement, for the
                    last reportable financial year;</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>presenting the financial statement and signed statement to the meeting for
                    adoption;</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>electing members of the management committee;</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>appointing an auditor, an accountant or an approved person for the present
                    financial year.</para>
            </listitem>
        </orderedlist>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Business to be conducted at annual general meeting of other level 3 incorporated
            associations</title>
        <para>This rule applies only if the association is a level 3 incorporated association to
            which section 59B of the Act applies.</para>
        <para>The following business must be conducted at each annual general meeting of the
            association-</para>
        <orderedlist numeration="loweralpha">
            <listitem>
                <para>receiving the association's financial statement, and signed statement, for the
                    last reportable financial year;</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>presenting the financial statement and signed statement to the meeting for
                    adoption;</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>electing members of the management committee.</para>
            </listitem>
        </orderedlist>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Notice of general meeting</title>
        <para>The secretary may call a general meeting of the association.</para>
        <para>The secretary must give at least 14 days notice of the meeting to each member of the
            association.</para>
        <para>If the secretary is unable or unwilling to call the meeting, the president must call
            the meeting.</para>
        <para>The management committee may decide the way in which the notice must be given.</para>
        <para>However, notice of the following meetings must be given in writing-</para>
        <orderedlist numeration="loweralpha">
            <listitem>
                <para>a meeting called to hear and decide the appeal of a person against the
                    management committee's decision-</para>
                <orderedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>to reject the person's application for membership of the association;
                            or</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>to terminate the person's membership of the association;</para>
                    </listitem>
                </orderedlist>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>a meeting called to hear and decide a proposed special resolution of the
                    association.</para>
            </listitem>
        </orderedlist>
        <para>A notice of a general meeting must state the business to be conducted at the
        meeting.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Quorum for, and adjournment of, general meeting</title>
        <para>The quorum for a general meeting is at least the number of members elected or
            appointed to the management committee at the close of the association's last general
            meeting plus 1.</para>
        <para>However, if all the members of the association are members of the management
            committee, the quorum is the total number of members less 1.</para>
        <para>No business may be conducted at a general meeting unless there is a quorum of members
            when the meeting proceeds to business.</para>
        <para>If there is no quorum within 30 minutes after the time fixed for a general meeting
            called on the request of members of the management committee of the association, the
            meeting lapses.</para>
        <para>If there is no quorum within 40 minutes after the time fixed for a general meeting
            called other than on request of members of the management committee or the association-</para>
        <orderedlist numeration="loweralpha">
            <listitem>
                <para>the meeting is to be adjourned for at least 7 days; and</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>the management committee is to decide the day, time, and place of the
                    adjourned meeting.</para>
            </listitem>
        </orderedlist>
        <para>The chairperson may, with the consent of any meeting at which there is a quorum, and
            must if directed by the meeting, adjourn the meeting from time to time and from place to
            place.</para>
        <para>If a meeting is adjourned under subrule (6), only the business left unfinished at the
            meeting from which adjournment took place may be conducted at the adjourned meeting.</para>
        <para>The secretary is not required to give the members notice of an adjournment or of the
            business to be conducted at an adjourned meeting unless a meeting is adjourned for at
            least 30 days.</para>
        <para>If a meeting is adjourned for at least 30 days, notice of the adjourned meeting must
            be given in the same way notice is given for an original meeting.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Procedure at general meeting</title>
        <para>A member may take part and vote in a general meeting in person, by proxy, by attorney,
            or by using any technology that reasonably allows the member to hear and take part in
            discussions as they happen.</para>
        <para>A member who participates in a meeting as mentioned in subrule (1) is taken to be
            present at the meeting.</para>
        <para>At each general meeting-</para>
        <orderedlist numeration="loweralpha">
            <listitem>
                <para>the president is to preside as chairperson; and</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>if there is no president or if the president is not present within 15 minutes
                    after the time fixed for the meeting or is unwilling to act, the members present
                    must elect 1 of their number to be chairperson of the meeting; and</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>the chairperson must conduct the meeting in a proper and orderly way.</para>
            </listitem>
        </orderedlist>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Voting at a general meeting</title>
        <para>At a general meeting, each question, matter or resolution, other than a special
            resolution, must be decided by a majority of votes of the members present.</para>
        <para>Each member present and eligible to vote is entitled to 1 vote only and, if the votes
            are equal, the chairperson has a casting vote as well as a primary vote.</para>
        <para>A member is not entitled to vote at a general meeting if the member's annual
            subscription is in arrears at the date of the meeting.</para>
        <para>The method of voting is to be decided by the management committee.</para>
        <para>However, if at least 20% of the members present demand a secret ballot, voting must be
            by secret ballot.</para>
        <para>If a secret ballot is held, the chairperson must appoint 2 members to conduct the
            secret ballot in the way the chairperson decides.</para>
        <para>The result of a secret ballot as declared by the chairperson is taken to be a
            resolution of the meeting at which the ballot was held.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Special general meeting</title>
        <para>The secretary must call a special general meeting by giving each member of the
            association notice of the meeting within 14 days after-</para>
        <orderedlist numeration="loweralpha">
            <listitem>
                <para>being directed to call the meeting by the management committee; or</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>being given a written request signed by-</para>
                <orderedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>at least 33% of the number of members of the management committee when
                            the request is signed; or</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>at least the number of ordinary members of the association equal to
                            double the number of members of the association on the management
                            committee when the request is signed plus 1; or</para>
                    </listitem>
                </orderedlist>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>being given a written notice of an intention to appeal against the decision of
                    the management committee-</para>
                <orderedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>to reject an application for membership; or</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>to terminate a person’s membership.</para>
                    </listitem>
                </orderedlist>
            </listitem>
        </orderedlist>
        <para>A request mentioned in subrule (1)(b) must state-</para>
        <orderedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para>why the special general meeting is being called; and</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>the business to be conducted at the meeting.</para>
            </listitem>
        </orderedlist>
        <para>A special general meeting must be held within 3 months after the secretary-</para>
        <orderedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para>is directed to call the meeting by the management committee; or</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>is given the written request mentioned in subrule (1)(b); or</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>is given the written notice of an intention to appeal mentioned in subrule
                    (1)(c).</para>
            </listitem>
        </orderedlist>
        <para>If the secretary is unable or unwilling to call the special meeting, the president
            must call the meeting.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Proxies</title>
        <para>An instrument appointing a proxy must be in writing and be in the following or similar
            form-</para>
        <blockquote>
            <para>[Name of association]:</para>
            <para>I, .................... of .................... being .................... of
                .................... as my proxy to vote for me on behalf at the (annual) general
                meeting of the association, to be held on the .... day of .... and at any
                adjournment of the meeting.</para>
            <para>Signed .... day of ....</para>
            <para>Signature</para>
        </blockquote>
        <para>The instrument appointing a proxy must-</para>
        <orderedlist numeration="loweralpha">
            <listitem>
                <para>if the appointer is an individual-be signed by the appointer or the
                    appointer's attorney properly authorised in writing; or</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>if the appointer is a corporation-</para>
                <orderedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>be under seal; or</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>be signed by a properly authorised officer or attorney of the
                            corporation.</para>
                    </listitem>
                </orderedlist>
            </listitem>
        </orderedlist>
        <para>A proxy may be a member of the association or another person.</para>
        <para>The instrument appointing a proxy is taken to confer authority to demand or join in
            demanding a secret ballot.</para>
        <para>Each instrument appointing a proxy must be given to the secretary before the start of
            the meeting or adjourned meeting at which the person named in the instrument proposes to
            vote.</para>
        <para>Unless otherwise instructed by the appointer, the proxy may vote as the proxy
            considers appropriate.</para>
        <para>If a member wants a proxy to vote for or against a resolution, the instrument
            appointing the proxy must be in the following or similar form-</para>
        <blockquote>
            <para>[Name of association]:</para>
            <para>I, .................... of .................... being a member of the association
                appoint .................... of .................... as my proxy to vote for me on
                behalf at the (annual) general meeting of the association, to be held on the ....
                day of .... and at any adjournment of the meeting.</para>
            <para>Signed .... day of ....</para>
            <para>Signature</para>
            <para>This form is to be used *in favour of/*against [strike out whichever is not
                wanted] the following resolutions-</para>
            <para>[List relevant resolutions]</para>
        </blockquote>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Minutes of general meetings</title>
        <para>The secretary must ensure full and accurate minutes of all questions, matters,
            resolutions and other proceedings of each general meeting are entered in a minute book.</para>
        <para>To ensure the accuracy of the minutes-</para>
        <orderedlist numeration="loweralpha">
            <listitem>
                <para>the minutes of each general meeting must be signed by the chairperson of the
                    meeting, or the chairperson of the next general meeting, verifying their
                    accuracy; and</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>the minutes of each annual general meeting must be signed by the chairperson
                    of the meeting, or the chairperson of the next meeting of the association that
                    is a general meeting or annual general meeting, verifying their accuracy.</para>
            </listitem>
        </orderedlist>
        <para>If asked by a member of the association, the secretary must, within 28 days after the
            request is made</para>
        <orderedlist numeration="loweralpha">
            <listitem>
                <para>make the minute book for a particular general meeting available for inspection
                    by the member at a mutually agreed time and place; and</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>give the member copies of the minutes of the meeting.</para>
            </listitem>
        </orderedlist>
        <para>The association may require the member to pay the reasonable costs of providing copies
            of the minutes.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>By-laws</title>
        <para>The management committee may make, amend or repeal by-laws, not inconsistent with
            these rules, for the internal management of the association.</para>
        <para>A by-law may be set aside by a vote of members at a general meeting of the
            association.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Alteration of rules</title>
        <para>Subject to the Act, these rules may be amended, repealed or added to by a special
            resolution carried at a general meeting.</para>
        <para>However an amendment, repeal or addition is valid only if it is registered by the
            chief executive.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Common seal</title>
        <para>The management committee must ensure the association has a common seal.</para>
        <para>The common seal must be-</para>
        <orderedlist numeration="loweralpha">
            <listitem>
                <para>kept securely by the management committee; and</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>used only under the authority of the management committee.</para>
            </listitem>
        </orderedlist>
        <para>Each instrument to which the seal is attached must be signed by a member of the
            management committee and countersigned by-</para>
        <orderedlist numeration="loweralpha">
            <listitem>
                <para>the secretary; or</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>another member of the management committee; or</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>someone authorised by the management committee.</para>
            </listitem>
        </orderedlist>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Funds and accounts</title>
        <para>The funds of the association must be kept in an account in the name of the association
            in a financial institution decided by the management committee.</para>
        <para>Records and accounts must be kept in the English language showing full and accurate
            particulars of the financial affairs of the association.</para>
        <para>All amounts must be deposited in the financial institution account as soon as
            practicable after receipt.</para>
        <para>A payment by the association of $100 or more must be made by cheque or electronic
            funds transfer.</para>
        <para>If a payment of $100 or more is made by cheque, the cheque must be signed by any 2 of
            the following-</para>
        <orderedlist numeration="loweralpha">
            <listitem>
                <para>the president;</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>the secretary;</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>the treasurer;</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>any 1 of 3 other members of the association who have been authorised by the
                    management committee to sign cheques issued by the association.</para>
            </listitem>
        </orderedlist>
        <para>However, 1 of the persons who signs the cheque must be the president, the secretary or
            the treasurer.</para>
        <para>Cheques, other than cheques for wages, allowances or petty cash recoupment, must be
            crossed 'not negotiable'.</para>
        <para>A petty cash account must be kept on the imprest system, and the management committee
            must decide the amount of petty cash to be kept in the account.</para>
        <para>All expenditure must be approved or ratified at a management committee meeting.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>General financial matters</title>
        <para>On behalf of the management committee, the treasurer must, as soon as practicable
            after the end date of each financial year, ensure a financial statement for its last
            reportable financial year is prepared.</para>
        <para>The income and property of the association must be used solely in promoting the
            association’s objects and exercising the association’s powers.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Documents</title>
        <para>The management committee must ensure the safe custody of books, documents, instruments
            of title and securities of the association.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Financial Year</title>
        <para>The end date of the association’s financial year is <emphasis>the last day of
            June</emphasis> in each year.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Distribution of surplus assets to another entity</title>
        <para>This rule applies if the association-</para>
        <orderedlist numeration="loweralpha">
            <listitem>
                <para>is wound-up under part 10 of the Act; and</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>has surplus assets</para>
            </listitem>
        </orderedlist>
        <para>The surplus assets must not be distributed among the members of the association.</para>
        <para>The surplus assets must be given to another entity-</para>
        <orderedlist numeration="loweralpha">
            <listitem>
                <para>having objects similar to the association’s objects; and</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>the rules of which prohibit the distribution of the entity’s income and assets
                    to its members.</para>
            </listitem>
        </orderedlist>
        <para>In this rule</para>
        <para><emphasis>surplus assets</emphasis> see section 92(3) of the Act.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Association to be not-for-profit</title>
        <para>The properties, assets, and income of the association shall be solely used to further
            the objects of the association, and no portion shall be distributed either directly or
            indirectly to the members of the association except as bona fide compensation for
            services rendered or expenses incurred on behalf of the association.</para>
        <para>The association shall comply with the Australian Tax Office requirements of
            not-for-profit associations in its actions.</para>
    </section>
</article>
